A Guide to the Papers of Louis Jaffé, ca. 1919-1956
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Louis I. Jaffé ca. 1919-1956
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9924-c
Ca. 540 items in 1 box.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé papers was a gift from Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé on 28 October 1975.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis I. Jaffé was born in Detroit, Michigan, February 22, 1888, the son of Phillip and Lotta Maria (Kahn) Jaffé. When Jaffé was twelve years old, his family moved to Durham, North Carolina, and he graduated from high school there in 1907. In 1911, he received an A.B. degree from Trinity College (now Duke University).
While a student at Trinity, Jaffé edited The Chronicle, a campus weekly, and was associate editor of The Archive, a college monthly. After graduation, he joined the staff of the Durham Sun, but left a short time later to become a reporter and assistant city editor for the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
In 1917, Jaffé was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officer's Reserve Corps of the United States Army. He was re-commissioned in the Aviation Section 1918, and again in 1919 with the Service of Supply. He was honorably discharged in France, March 29, 1919, and was commissioned as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with rank of Captain. He served on the Red Cross Commission to the Balkans from April to July, 1919, and was director of the Red Cross News Service in Paris from July to October, 1919. He was made a Chevalier of the State of Roumania, and honor bestowed in recognition of his work there with the Red Cross Commission.
After the war, Jaffé went to Norfolk to become editor of the Virginian-Pilot, a position he held from 1919 until his death in 1950. He was prominent among Virginia liberal journalists and won the Pulitzer Prize in 1929 for an editorial deploring a lynching which took place in Houston, Texas, on the eve of the Democratic National Convention.
In one of his last editorials, dated February 25, 1950, concerning the "mercy killing" of the Boothe bill for desegregation of Virginia public transportation he wrote: "The Virginia Democratic organization makes haste slowly in the field of social-political reform...It is still too uneasy about the impact of de-segregation on common carries to give the proposal anything like an official blessing. That will come later-after a longer look at this highly desirable reform, and possibly after another shove or two from the Supreme Court of the United States."
Scope and Content
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé Papers, ca. 1919-1956, consists of ca. 540 items including Jaffé's correspondence files for "E," personal correspondence with the artist J.J. Lankes, and several items of Lankes memorabilia.
The Lankes correspondence (1929-1956) consists of ca. 340 letters and postcards, of which ca. 256 are from Lankes. They afford rich documentation for Lankes' life and opinions.
The correspondence file for "E," like the preceding files, contains commentary on a variety of topics including politics, race relations, and newspaper work in general.
Arrangement
The correspondence file is alphabetically arranged, with the individually labeled folders following the general "E" file. The Lankes correspondence is arranged chronologically and is followed by one folder of memorabilia.
Contents List
- Correspondence - General "E" 1919-1948, ca. 56 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with C.L. Edson, columnist, Mount Pleasant, S.C. 1921-1926, n.d., ca. 72 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Dwight D. Eisenhower 1948 July, 2 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Mrs. Henry Ely, Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs 1929-1931, ca. 14 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Mark Ethridge, Macon Telegraph, Washington Post, and other papers, and Mrs. Ethridge 1931-1937, 8 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with J.J. Lankes, artist; Hilton Village, Va.; Newport News, Va.; Wells College 1929-1931, ca. 86 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with J.J. Lankes, artist; Hilton Village, Va.; Newport News, Va.; Wells College 1932-1936, ca. 100 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with J.J. Lankes, artist; Hilton Village, Va.; Newport News, Va.; Wells College 1937-1942, ca. 110 items
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with J.J. Lankes, artist; Hilton Village, Va.; Wells College and one letter to A.R. (Mrs. Louis I.) Jaffé 1943-1949, 1956, ca. 79 items
- Miscellaneous woodcuts and items by J.J. Lankes ca. 1930-ca.1940, ca. 11 items